okay the this is the review uh lecture
for the first part of the course uh the
axal B part of the course uh and
um the exam will emphasize chapter 3
cuz those are the chapter 3 was about
the rectangular matrices where we had
null spaces and no spaces of a transpose
and ranks and all the things that are so
clear when the Matrix is square and
invertible they
became things to think about for uh
rectangular
matrices so uh and Vector spaces and sub
spaces and above all those four
subspaces okay I'm thinking to start at
least I'll just look at old exams read
out questions write on the board what I
need to and we can see what the answers
are uh the first one I see is one I can
just read out well I'll write a little
suppose U V and W are non non zero
vectors in r
s what are the possible they span a a
vector space they span a Subspace of our
s and what are the possible
Dimensions so it's a straightforward
question what are the possible
dimensions of the Subspace spaned by UV
and
W okay I
one two or three right one two or three
couldn't be more because we've only got
three
vectors and couldn't be zero
because
uh cuz I told you the vectors were
nonzero otherwise if if if I allowed the
possibility that those were all the zero
Vector then the Zero Dimensional
Subspace would have been in there okay
now can I jump to uh a more serious
question okay we have a 5x3
matrix and I'm calling it
U I'm saying it's in ealon form and it
has three pivots r equal three three
pivots okay first question what's the
null space
what's the null space of this Matrix U
so this Matrix is 5 by3 and I I find it
helpful
to just see visually what 5x3 means what
that shape is three columns three
columns in U then five rows three pivots
and what's the null space the null space
of U is
and it asks for a spe of course I'm
looking for an answer that isn't just
the definition of the null space but is
the null space of this Matrix with this
information and what is it it's only the
zero Vector because we're told that the
rank is three so those three columns
must be
independent no combination of those Comm
of those columns is the zero Vector
except so the only thing in this null
space is the zero vector and I could
even say what that Vector is 0 0 0
that's okay so that's what's in the null
space all right let me
go on with this question has multiple
Parts
um what's
the oh now it asks you about a 10x3
matrix B which is the Matrix U and 2 U
it actually I would probably be writing
R if uh if and maybe I should be writing
R here now the the this this exam goes
back a few years when I emphasized youu
more than
R uh now what's the echelon form for
that
Matrix so the echelon form what's the
rank and what's the echelon form
let's suppose this is in reduced Echelon
form so that I could be using the letter
R so I'll I'll ask for the reduced row
Echelon form so imagine that these are U
is
in reduced row Echelon form but now I've
got I've doubled the height of the
Matrix what will happen when we do row
reduction what row reduction will take
us to what Matrix
here so you start doing
elimination you're doing elimination on
single rows but of course we're allowed
to think of blocks so what well what's
the answer look like U and z or r i
let's I'll stay with this letter U but
I'm really thinking it's in reduced form
and zero
okay fine then uh it asks oh further it
asks about this
Matrix u u u and
zero okay what's the echelon form of
this so it's just like practice and
thinking through what would row
elimination what would row reduction
do have I thought this through so what
what are we if we start doing
elimination basically we're going to
subtract these rows from these so it's
going to take us
to U
u0 and minus U I guess
right take the thing all the way to uh R
let's let's suppose U is really R
suppose that we're really going for the
reduced row Echelon form then would we
stop there
no uh we would clean out we would we
could use this to is that right can I so
I took this row these rows away from
these to get there now I take these rows
away from these so that gives me
zero there and now what uh what more
would I do if I'm really shooting for R
the reduced row Echelon
form I I would then I want plus ones in
the pivot so I would multiply through by
minus one to get plus there so
essentially I'm
seeing uh reduced row Echelon form there
and there and and there's just one
little twist still to go do you see what
that final twist might
be uh to to
have if if U is in reduced row Echelon
form and now I'm looking at u u
there's one little step to take this
isn't like a big deal at all but but if
I really want this to be in reduced
form what would I still might might I
still have to
do I I might have some zero rows here I
might have some zero rows here that
strictly should move to the bottom well
I'm not going to make a project out of
that okay what's the rank of that Matrix
what's the rank of this Matrix
C given that I know that the original U
has rank
three what's the rank of this
guy six right that has rank six I can
tell what was what's the rank of this B
while while we're at
it the rank of B is that six or three
three is right three is Right CU we
actually got it to where we could just
see three pivots okay U and oh now
finally just easy one what's the
dimension of the null
space of the null space of C
transpose oh boy okay so what do I if I
want the dimension of a null space I
want to know the size of the Matrix so
what's the size of the Matrix
C it looks like
it's 10x 6 is it 10 by 6 so C is 10 by
6 so m is
10 so C has 10 row 10 rows C transpose
has 10 columns so there are 10 columns
there so how many free variables have I
got once I I start with the 10 columns
in C transpose that's the M for the
original
C and what do I subtract
off six because we said that was the
rank so I'm left with four thanks okay
so I think that's the right answer the
dimension of the null space of C
transpose would be four right okay yeah
okay let me so that that's one question
at least it um brought in um some some
of the uh Dimension counts okay here's
another type of
question I give you an
equation ax =
242 and I give you the complete
solution but I don't give you the Matrix
and another there
another Vector
okay all right my first question is
what's the dimension of the row
space of the Matrix a
so the main thing that you want to get
from this question is that a question
could start this
way sort of backward Way by by giving
you the answer and not telling you what
the problem is but we can get a lot of
information and sometimes we can get
complete information about that Matrix a
okay so what's the dimension of the row
space of a what's the rank tell tell me
about what's the size of the Matrix yeah
just this is these are the things we
want to think about what's the what's
the uh what what's the shape of the
Matrix first of
all it certainly has three
rows but is it all is it
3x3 the the X's that it multiplies have
three components so that just does the
Matrix have three columns also yes so
I'm seeing the same length in in B three
and also in a so a is a 3X3
Matrix and
uh what's the what's its
[Music]
rank it's
rank tell me something about it n space
I heard the right answer for the rank
the rank is one in this
case
why because was the dimension of the
null space so the
dimension of the null space of
a
is from knowing that that's the complete
solution it's two I'm seeing two vectors
here and they're independent in
the n space of a because they have to be
in the no space of a if I'm allowed to
throw in to the solution any amount of
those
vectors that tells me that's the no
space part then so the dimension of the
no space is two and then I of course I
know the dimensions of all the all all
four such
faces now actually it asks what's the
Matrix what's what's the Matrix in this
case
um do we want to shall I try to figure
that out
sure let's you'd like me to do it okay
uh so what about the Matrix or I'll let
me at least start it okay if a * this x
gives 242 what does that tell me about
the Matrix
a if a * that
X solves that equation then that tells
me that the First Column is
the First Column of a
is one 2 1 right the First Column of a
has to be 1 2 1 because if I multiply by
X that's going to multiply just the
First Column and give me 2 42 and then
I've got two more columns to
find and what information have I got to
find them
with I've got the null
space so the fact that this is in the
null space what does does that tell me
about the Matrix a matrix that has 0 01
in its null
space that tells me that the last column
of the Matrix is zero because this is in
the null space the last column has to be
zero and because this is in the null
space what's the second
[Music]
column well this in the n space means
that if I multiply a by that Vector I
must be getting zero so I think that
better be -1 -2 and
-1 okay that's a type of question that
just brings out the the information
that's in that complete
solution
okay and then actually I go on to ask
what vectors for what vectors B can axal
B be solved a x = b can be solved
if what so I'm looking for a condition
on B if any can it be solved for every
for every right hand side
B no definitely
not when could it be solved well what's
the I actually say in this in the in the
exam don't just tell me
if B is in the and what would what does
the exam say there in the column space
because I do know that uh that that it
can be solved exactly when B is in the
column space so I guess I'm asking you
what is the column space for this Matrix
so so what is if B has the
[Music]
form so I guess I'm asking you what's
the column space of this Matrix
and what is
it
it's uh so the column space of that
Matrix is all
multiples b b is a multiple of one 12
one
right I can solve the thing if it's a
multiple of one two one and of course
sure
enough uh this oh yeah that was a
multiple of one two one and so I had a
solution so this is a case where we've
got lots of null
space let me just
recall that the The Other Extreme when
the no when when the rank is Big don't
forget those those cases don't
forget don't forget the
other the
other
cases when R is as big as it can be Ral
M or Ral n those are those we had a full
lecture on that full rank full lecture
and uh important important case
okay I'll just move on I think this is
the best type of review it just brings
these ideas out uh apologies for the
camera while I recover glasses and and
uh exam okay
how about a few true false ones actually
there won't be a true false on the quiz
but it's it gives us a moment of quick
review
uh here's one if the null space I have a
square
Matrix if its null space is just the
zero
Vector what about the null space of a
transpose if the null space of a a is
just a zero vector and the Matrix is
square what do I know about the null
space of a
transpose also the Zer Vector good and
that's a very very important fact
okay uh how about
this the look at the space of 5x five
matrices as a vector
space so it's actually a 25 dimensional
Vector space all 5x5 matrices look at
the invertible
matrices do they form a
Subspace so I have this 5 by this this
space of all 5x five matrices I can add
them I can multiply by numbers but now I
narrow down to the invertible ones and I
ask are they a Subspace and you your
answer
is quiet but nevertheless
definite no
right no cuz if I add two invertible
matrices I have no idea if the answer is
invertible If I multiply that invertible
well it doesn't even have the zero
Matrix in it it couldn't be a
subst I have to be able to multiply by
zero and stay in my Subspace and the
invertible ones wouldn't work well the
the singular ones wouldn't work either
they have zero the zero Matrix is in the
singular matrices but
if I add two singular matrices I don't
know if the answer is singular or not
okay so uh another true
false if B here we go here's it if b^2
equals 0 then b equals Z true or false
if b^2 = 0 true
false b^2 = 0 B has to be a square
square Matrix so that I can multiply by
itself does that
[Music]
that b is
zero are there matrices whose square
could be the zero
Matrix yes or no yes there
are there are matrices whose square is
the zero Matrix so this statement is
false if b^2 is z we don't know that b
is z for example the best thing example
is that Matrix that Matrix is a is a
dangerous Matrix it uh it will come up
in later parts of this course as an
example of what can go wrong and here is
a real simple so this so if I square
that Matrix I do get the zero
Matrix uh and it shows of
course uh yeah yeah okay
all right
um here here a system
of okay a system of n equations in N
unknowns is
solvable for every right hand side if
the columns are
independent okay can I say that again
it's I'll write it down then for short n
by
n Matrix independent
columns then the question is does axal B
is it always
Sol and the answer is yes yes or no
right okay um which let's see let's
have did you watch that quiz there was a
quiz uh program on TV for a few weeks
did you see that what was the name of
that winning a million dollars or
something how to be a millionaire with
some crazy guy what was his name as the
MC reges right reges okay if you saw
this like when you should have been
doing Vine alra of course um uh but I
didn't have to do the homework so I was
watching it uh
so there were three the the interesting
the novel point was there were three
ways that you could get help right uh
but you could only use each way once so
you couldn't like use them all the time
so you remember that you could so you
could pull the audience and that was a
very that was 100% successful way so
I'll pull the audience on this uh if if
uh the other possibility another
possibility you could call your friend
right or he's your friend until he gives
you the wrong
answer that that turned out to be very
unreliable you know you call up your
brother or something and ask him for the
capital of whatever Bosnia what does he
know he makes some guest and it cost you
half a million so uh but let's but
calling the audience always works uh so
what's let me let me say yes if I yes or
no if I have Square Matrix independent
columns is ax B always solvable maybe
just hands up for
that few and who says
no oh gosh this audience is not
reliable 50
50 um I guess I'd say I'd vote Yes
because uh independent columns that
means that the rank is the full size N I
have a matrix of rank n uh that means
it's I mean it's Square so it's an
invertible Matrix and nothing nothing
could go wrong yeah so that's that's the
good case that we always expected in
Chapter 2 but of course chapter 3 is
that's uh uh only one of the
possibilities okay let me let me move on
to uh another
um uh
another uh question from an old quiz
okay
okay um let's
[Applause]
see um okay I'm going to give you a
matrix but I'm going to give it to you
as a product of a couple of matrices 1 1
Z 0 1
0 1 0
times another Matrix 1 0 -1
2 0 1 1
-1 and all
zeros
okay I would like to ask you questions
about that
Matrix
without doing the
multiplication and finding the Matrix B
can you can you tell me something can we
can I so I'll ask questions about this
Matrix B and I'll answer them without
multiplying it out for example I'm going
to ask you for a basis for the null
space a basis for the null
space so I'm going to solve BX = Z so so
give me a basis
for for the null space of
B let's see what dimension am I in what
what this the null space of B is the
Subspace of
R what size vectors am I looking for
here cuz if we don't know the size we
aren't going to find it right
the N this Matrix is 3x4
obviously so if we're looking for the
null space we're looking for those
vectors X in R4 okay so the null space
of B is certainly a Subspace of
R4 what do you think its Dimension is of
course once we find the basis we would
know the dimension immediately but let
stop first what's the rank of this
Matrix
B uh let's see what that Matrix is that
Matrix invertible that square one
there let's say sure I think it is yeah
yeah yes that Matrix B looks in
verbal is that is that pretty clear
yeah yeah Al so I've gone wrong in this
uh course already
but I'll I'll still hope that that
Matrix is Inver yeah yeah because if I
look for a combination of those three
columns well I couldn't use uh this
middle column because it would have a
one in in a in in a position that I that
that only is otherwise all zero so a
combination that gives zero can't use
that column and then the other two are
clearly independent except so that
Matrix is
invertible later we could take it
determinant or other things okay
uh what's the setup if I have an
invertible Matrix a nice invertible
Square Matrix times this
guy that's a second factor and I'm
looking for the null space does this
have any
effect is the n so what I'm asking is is
the null space of B the same as the
space of just this
part I think
so I think
so if if BX is zero then multiplying by
that guy I'll still have zero but also
if if this time some X gives zero I
could always multiply on the left by the
inverse of that because it is invertible
and I would discover that this time
times the x is Z
just you want me to write some of that
down if I have a product here C
* times uh D
say and if C is
invertible the null
space of CD will will be the same as the
null space of D if C is
inverted multiplying by an invert Matrix
on the left can't change the null
space okay so basically I'm asking you
for the null space of this
one I don't have to do the
multiplication because I'm CU I see is
in that first factor C is
invertible it's not going to change the
nement okay so can we just write down a
basis now for the no space so what's the
basis for the no space of that so so
basis
for the null
space I'm looking for the
two there are two pivot columns
obviously it clearly has rank two I'm
looking for the two special Solutions
they'll come from the third and the
fourth the free variables okay so if the
third free variable is a one then I
think probably I need a minus one there
and a one there looks like you agree
that if I then do that multiplication
I'll get zero and if I have one in the
fourth variable then maybe I need a one
in the second variable and maybe a minus
2 in the 3 so I just reason that through
and then if I look back I see sure
enough that the free variable part that
I sometimes call F that up that two by
two corner is sitting here with all its
signs
reversed so that's here I'm seeing minus
F and here I'm seeing the identity in
the null space Matrix okay so that's the
null space uh another question is solve
BX =
101 okay so that was that's one question
now solve complete solution
to BX
equals
okay yeah so I guess I'm seeing if I
wanted to get
one1 what's what's a particular solution
so I'm looking for a particular solution
and then the null space part
okay actually the first column of
B what's the First Column of our Matrix
B it's the vector
101 the First Column of our Matrix
agrees with the right hand side so I I
guess I'm thinking X particular plus x n
space will be the particular solution
since the first column of B is exactly
right that's great and then I have c
times that first null space vector and B
times the other no space
Vector right the two the the the no
space part of the solution as always is
as the has the uh arbitrary constants
the particular solution doesn't have any
arbitrary constants it's one particular
solution and in this case it that one
would do it okay fine
uh so that those are questions taken
from old quizzes any questions coming to
mind yeah I don't understand how you got
particular this x particular guy okay
well so that particular X particular
uh says
that see when I multiply by this guy I'm
going to get the First Column of
B that if that's a solution when I when
I multiply b b * this x will be the
first column of B and so I'm saying that
the First Column of this
B agrees with the right hand side so I'm
saying that look at the look at the
First Column of that Matrix B if you do
the
multiplication it's so what's the first
column of that Matrix is that how do you
do that multiplication I multiply that
matrix by that First Column and it picks
one1 so the first problem of B is
exactly
that and therefore a particular solution
will be this
guy
yeah okay yes is particular solution is
there only one particular solution no
not at all no I could uh I mean this is
a nice one but any solution could be the
particular solution
any any of the solutions can be the
particular one that we pick
out um so so uh like this
plus plus this would be another
particular solution it would be in other
words it be another
solution particular is just telling us
only take one but it's not telling us
which one we have to take we take the
most convenient one I guess in this in
this problem that that one good other
questions yeah and and this pattern of
particular plus null space of course
that's going
throughout mathematics of linear
systems we're really doing mathematics
of linear systems here our systems are
discreet and they're finite dimensional
and so it's linear algebra
but this particular plus null space goes
that doesn't depend on having finite
matrices that that go that spreads much
spreads
everywhere okay I'm going to just like
to encourage you to take problems out of
the book let me do the same
myself
um okay well here's some easy true or
falses
I don't know why the author put these in
here
okay ifal n then the row space equals
the column space so these are true
falses if m equal n so that means the
Matrix is square then the row space
equals the column
space false good good what is equal
there what can I say is equal if well
yeah
yeah it so that's definitely false the
row space and the column space and and
this Matrix is like always a good
example to consider so there's a square
Matrix but its row
space is the multiples of 01 and its
column space is the multiples of one
zero very different the row space and
column space are totally different for
that Matrix now of course if the Matrix
was symmetric
well then clearly the row space equals
the column okay um how about this
question the matrices a and minus a
share the same four
subspaces do the matrices a and minus a
have the same column space do they have
the same null space do they have same
row space what's the answer on that yes
or no yes good
okay uh how about this if a and b have
the same four subspaces then a is a
multiple of
B if suppose suppose those subspaces are
the
same then is a a multiple of
B okay just I don't how do you answer a
question like
that of course if you want to answer it
yes then I would then you'd have to
think think of a reason why if you want
to answer no way then you would and and
and I would sort of like first I would
try to think
no I would say can I come up with an
example where it isn't
true let me repeat the question and then
write the answer okay so I'll repeat
that question if so true or false if a
and b have the same
four
subspaces
then a is some multiple of
B true or false how do you how do you
feel about at this
inst got quite a few true so I take a
pole so how many think
true
okay gave you every chance to think
about that
uh let's see so what I would just take
extreme cases if it was me
uh so when do I
know well I would suppose a matrix is
invertible suppose a is an invertible
Matrix then what suppose it's 6x6
invertible Matrix then what's its row
space
and it column space is all
of R
six and the null space and the n space
of a transposed would
be the zero Vector so every invertible
Matrix is going to give that
answer if I have a 6x6 invertible Matrix
I know what those subspaces are heck
that was back in Chapter 2 when I didn't
even know what sub spaces
were the row space and column space are
both all six dimensional space the whole
space and the rank is six in other words
and the null spaces have zero Dimension
so do you see now the
answer so A and B could be for example
any so I'm going to say
false because A and B for example so an
example A and B
any
invertible
6x6
6x6 so those would have the same four
subspaces but they wouldn't be the same
of course there should be something
about those matrices that would be the
same so it's sort of a natural problem
so now actually we're getting to a math
question the answer
is this is not true
one Matrix doesn't have to be a multiple
of the other but some there must be
something that's
true and that would be sort of like a
natural question to ask if they have the
same subspaces same four subspaces then
what what uh could you uh you know what
could you then say about those
matrices yeah maybe I I'll let me leave
that as a as an open question just sort
of the for for uh uh uh cuz the Instinct
wasn't necessarily
right but I hope you now see that the
the correct answer is false and then you
might think okay well they certainly do
have the same
rank but
do
um obviously if they have the same four
sub spaces they have the same
rank uh I might say if they have this 12
yeah yeah I could extend that question
and think about other possibilities and
finally come up with something that was
true uh but I won't uh um press that one
let me let me keep going with practice
question and these practice questions
are quite uh appropriate I think for the
exam okay
uh let's
see if if I exchange two rows of a which
subspaces stay the
same so I'm trying to take out questions
that we can answer without you know we
can answer quickly if I if I have a
matrix a and I exchange two of its rows
which subspaces stay the
same the row space does stay the
same and the no space good good correct
column place would be a wrong answer
okay uh oh here's a question oh this
leads into a next chapter why can the
vector 1 2 3 not be a row and also in
the n space let me let me close with
this question closes so V this this 1 2
3 can't
be in the null space of a matrix
and the row
space and my question is why not why
not so this is a question that we can
cuz it's sort of asked in a
straightforward way we can figure out an
answer well actually yeah
I'll even pin it down it can't be in the
no space and and be a
row I'll even pin it down further ask
you ask it to be a row of
a why
not so I'm this is now I'm we know the
dimensions of these
spaces but now I'm asking you sort of
like the overlap between so the null
space and the row space those are in the
same nend dimensional
space those are those are both subspaces
of nend dimensional space and I'm
basically saying they can't
overlap I can't have a vector like this
typical Vector that's in the null space
and it's also a row of the Matrix why is
that so that's a new sort of idea let's
just see what it would mean I mean that
a * this
V why can this a * this V it can't be
zero oh well if if it's
zero so this is I'm getting it into the
null space
here so this is now let's put that ve
now that Vector is in the null space why
can't one why can't the first row of the
Matrix be 1 2 3
I can fill out the Matrix as I like why
is that
impossible now you're seeing it's
impossible
right and that if that was a row of the
Matrix and in the null space that number
would not be zero it would be
14 right so now we actually are
beginning to get a more complete picture
of these four
subspaces the two that are over in in in
nend dimensional
space they actually only share the zero
VOR the intersection of the null space
and the row space is only the
zero and in fact the null space is
perpendicular to the Rose space that'll
be the first topic on let's see we have
a holiday Monday and I'll see you
Wednesday with
perpendiculars and I'll see a price so
good luck on the
[Music]
way